Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף כ"א. daf
chaf aleph. We have the wonderful opportunity first because we fell a
little behind of finishing off דף כ' daf chaf today. So we
pick up with the bottom of כ' עמוד ב' chaf amud bet
and it is
ולא תתורו אחרי לבבכם. velo tasuru acharei levavchem. Okay, so we had
just gone through a big גמרא Gemara actually in all of ש"ס
Shas that really deals with the question about what type of acts
are permissible for husband and wife during the act of marital sex
and had the position of, you know, אמא שלום Imma Shalom and
יוחנן בן דהבאי, Yochanan ben Dahavai, you know, that was much more
like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, implicitly אמא שלום's Imma Shalom husband, that
was implicitly much more... that was... it wasn't implicitly... much more restrictive,
seemed to have a lot more of anxiety about the sex act,
about doing things the right way, and the possible improprieties about certain
type of acts or certain type of thoughts and so on, you
know, very sort of fascinating story about how רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
would rush through the act lest he have an improper thought. And
then the, you know, and then the opposing voice of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan because יוחנן בן דהבאי Yochanan ben Dahavai is like even
a הלכתי halakhic voice that says אין הלכה כיוחנן בן דהבאי אלא
כל מה שאדם רוצה לעשות באשתו עושה, ein halakhah k'Yochanan ben Dahavai,
ella kol mah she-adam rotzeh la'asot b'ishto oseh, again very much from
the male perspective, it gets paraphrased nowadays as the couple can do
whatever they want, but from the גמרא Gemara the man can do
whatever he wants with his wife and, you know, no sense of
like a fundamental sense of like not like it's problematic but you
can still do it. Like a fundamental sense like it's completely unproblematic.
Like why should there be any issue? You can do whatever you
want between the two of you and that's totally and that's totally
fine. And
now there's some points I wanted to make about... Oh yes, so
it is interesting, right, that the גמרא Gemara right sort of starts
with this question about how the kid is going to turn out,
which obviously reflects a sense that that act is problematic and therefore
it'll affect the kid in a bad way. And then when רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan sort of frames this as אין הלכה, ein halakhah,
he makes it like a הלכתי halakhic statement, which obviously if it's
a הלכתי halakhic statement, רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan voice is going to
be much more important than יוחנן בן דהבאי, Yochanan ben Dahavai, you
know, whatever, who's יוחנן בן דהבאי? Yochanan ben Dahavai? And the גמרא
Gemara sort of recognizes the problem with this. Well maybe it wasn't
a הלכתי halakhic position. Maybe it was just a position of how
actually metaphysically it affects the kid. And it turns יוחנן בן דהבאי
Yochanan ben Dahavai and the מלאכי השרת, malachei ha-shareit, the heavenly angels,
into רבנן, rabbanan, some anonymous rabbis. So you know, it's like once
you're on my territory, like once I've got you like you know
fighting on my turf, if we're talking about הלכה, halakhah, then it's
a way of completely rejecting it. But also it's another... you know
there's something powerful about this, which is don't let these you know
like these anxieties and metaphysics and you know this other type of
baggage get confused with הלכה. halakhah. Like whatever ideas you might have
as proper, not proper, whatever, you know that's like completely coming from
a non-הלכתי halakhic place. הלכתית halakhically like there's nothing problematic here. Okay,
but now though the גמרא Gemara makes an important shift. And now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ולא תתורו velo tasuru
now about six lines before the lines get wide. ולא תתורו אחרי
לבבכם—you velo tasuru acharei levavchem shall not stray after your hearts. מכאן
אמר רבי Rebbe אל ישתה אדם בכוס זה ויתן עיניו בכוס אחר.
mikan amar Rebbe, al yishateh adam b'kos zeh v'yiten einov b'kos acher.
A person should not drink from one cup and be thinking about
another cup. Again as a metaphor for having sex. Should not be
having sex with his wife and thinking about another woman. אמר רבינא
לא נצרכה אלא דאפילו בשתי נשיו.
amar Ravina lo nitzrecha
ella d'afillu b'shnei nashav. And this doesn't even mean a woman he's
not married to. It means even if he's married to two wives,
he shouldn't be having sex with one and thinking about the other.
Okay, so it's actually interesting because it's like ולא תתורו velo tasuru
like אחרי לבבכם ואחרי עיניכם. acharei levavchem v'acharei eineichem. עיניכם eineichem means
you're seeing something else. Here it's the opposite: it focuses, I think,
I mean you could say it's referring to the end of the
פסוק, pasuk, but I think it's referring to אחרי לבבכם. acharei levavchem.
No, you... the man is seeing the woman in front of him
but he's being strayed after his heart, after what... after something he's
thinking about as you know as opposed to something that he is
that he is seeing the wife the woman in front of him.
And so this now is not talking about the problematic being in
terms of what type of act is being done, what type of
physical act, but what... whether the act of sex is about relating
to the person in front of you or I would say using
the person in front of you. Man using his wife as a...
as a stand-in for the woman he really imagines himself and wants
to be having and wants to be having sex with. And that
is the problem, not the type of activity. I should say that
there's an important question here, you know, about what do you call
it, about the role of fantasy in a... in a married life
because, you know, fantasy's like an important part of keeping people, you
know, stimulated and excited and so on. But, you know, is that
a problem if somebody fantasizes, you know, about this? And some... some
פוסקים poskim think it is, you know, that... but to me it
seems that this גמרא Gemara is talking only very much if somebody
is using the person in front of them like literally as like
a stand-in, like they imagine themselves having sex with another person and
this person is like the is like playing that role, you know
what I'm saying, is like not your fantasizing as a way to
get yourself aroused and then
you're actually... Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: וברותי מכם
המורדים והפושעים בי, Uvaroti mikem hamordim vehaposheim bi, and out in
a similar vein, וברותי מכם המורדים והפושעים בי. Uvaroti mikem hamordim vehaposheim
bi.
I will sift out from you, or select out from you, those
that rebel and sin against me. אמר רבי לוי אלו בני תשע
מדות. Amar Rabbi Levi elu bnei tisha middot. These are the children
of people of nine character, character traits, מדות, middot, meaning nine types
of acts of sex that were done incorrectly will create children, will
lead to the conception of children that will rebel against me, improper
children. So again, remember yesterday, how did children become improper, physically improper?
They became physically improper because of some type of what's an improper
physical act, which then the גמרא Gemara rejected, that it's not an
improper act. Now it's talking about how the children will come out
improper, more improper in terms of their not physical nature, but improper
in terms of their attitude, right, in terms of character, and the
problem here is not going to be a physical problem, the problem
here is going to be a problem of character, or of מדות.
middot. Let's take a look. Okay. אמר רבי לוי אלו בני תשע
מדות. Amar Rabbi Levi elu bnei tisha middot. These are the children
of nine character traits, of nine types of actions.
בני אסנ"ת משגע"ח. Bnei Asnat Mashgaach. So what does that mean? So
that's obviously an acronym. בני אימה, Bnei Eima, that the husband is
having sex with his wife but she's afraid of him. So she
is, you know, she is, you know, she's agreeing to do things
because she's afraid of what he might do to her if she
doesn't go along.
Maybe she's also scared about all the stuff we've been having before?
No, no, not, anyway. You look at the ר"ן: Ran: לשון יראה
שהטיל אימה על אשתו להזקק לו
שלא כרצונה. Lashon yira shehetil eima al ishto lehizakek lo shelo kirtzonah.
Okay, which doesn't, you know again, there's like this whole question
about like in the act itself is she saying no, no, or
is she like she really wanted to say no, but she's saying
yes because she's afraid of him?
So that's אימה. Eima. Then it gets even worse, which is בני
אנוסה, Bnei Anusa, literally raped. בני שנואה, Bnei Senuah, if she is,
if he hates her. So, you know, he has absolutely no love,
no care for her, but you know, she's his wife, might as
well have sex, might as well get pleasure. The ראב"ד, Ra'avad, although
a lot of these are focused on the man's attitude towards the
woman, the ראב"ד Ra'avad when he discusses this גמרא Gemara makes it
parallel, says: he hates her or she hates him, either way, right?
Doesn't matter. The point is that one of them is not relating
to the other, is using the other person just to have sex
and is not actually relating to them out of love or care
or concern.
There should be another one, בני אחרת, Bnei Achereit, which is touch-me.
Okay, well we're going to get to that. בני נידוי, Bnei Miduy,
so this is really the one that's unrelated to all of these.
He's under a ban and therefore shouldn't be having sex, so he's
just violating a הלכה halachic prohibition by having sex. That's the least
interesting, it's not related to these. בני תמורה, Bnei Tmurah, exchange, which
means that he actually is thinking he's sleeping with one wife and
he winds up sleeping with the other, okay? So something along those
lines.
So you have יעקב Yaakov and... Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, it's a good point. Right,
exactly. That's, well maybe she didn't conceive on that night.
Exactly, exactly. Okay.
Okay, so that, בני מריבה, Bnei Meriva, they're in the middle of
fighting. So maybe they don't hate each other, but they're right now
in the middle of a fight and this is not makeup sex
after the fight, this is when they're still fighting. But again, it's
like, okay, I'm really angry at you and we're having a fight,
but you know what, we might as well have sex. So בני
שכרות, Bnei Shichrut, okay, or they're drunk. Again, one of them, according
to the ראב"ד Ra'avad it means even one of them is drunk.
Again, not really in the right mind, not doing it with a
sense of like fully being mentally
present, okay. בני גרושת הלב, Bnei Grushat Halev, divorced in the heart.
The husband is planning on divorcing his wife, he doesn't even have
to have told her because it's unilateral. And again, he's just basically
okay, but until we get to that, I might as well have
sex. Okay, so בני ערבוביא, Bnei Irvuvya, בני חצופה. Bnei Chatzufa. Children
of confusion. So confusion here, I mean the ר"ן Ran says, I
mean this is like much more extreme, שבאו עליה כמה בני אדם.
Shebo'u aleha kama bnei adam. So I don't know, I mean that's
like, why that should be like even a case of what do
you call it, of like,
right, of adultery.
רש"י Rashi has another case, like maybe he doesn't know which of
his wives he's having sex with, which is similar to the previous
case. So that one's a little confusing exactly what it's about. And
בני חצופה, Bnei Chatzufa, she is,
she has חוצפה, chutzpah, she's too audacious, and we'll see what that
means in a minute. So other than תמורה Tmurah and the חוצפה
chutzpah we'll get to in a minute, all of them are
basically because you're just using the other person for sex, it's a
means of self-gratification and it is not a form of relating to
the person and connecting to the person in front of you. And
that is really how powerful this גמרא Gemara is because yesterday it
was like oh, this act of sex is wrong, that act, somehow
there's
something... You can do whatever you want. What's the problem is, and
what will impact the kids, is not what will impact them physically,
but what will impact their character, and what will impact them is
how you're relating to your wife, or if we want to make
it more reciprocal, how the couple, how
each person relates to his or her partner. And that is ultimately
what determines what הלכה Halacha demands from the act of sex. Not
a particular type of an act, but sex as a way of
connecting to the other person and not as using the other person.
And now we turn to the issue of
בני חצופה, Bnei Chatzufa, which is audacity,
which the גמרא Gemara understands to mean that the woman demands to
have sex with her husband, and that's seen as improper. So the
גמרא Gemara says איני, Ayni, is that really true? דאמר רב שמואל
בר נחמני אמר רבי יוחנן, De'amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi
Yochanan, כל אדם שאשתו תובעתו, kol adam she'ishto tova'ato, any man that
his wife demands to have sex with him, הויין לו בנים שאפילו
בדורו של משה רבינו לא היו כמותם, havin lo banim she'afilu b'doro
shel Moshe Rabbeinu lo hayu kemosam, will have children that even in
the generation of משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu there were none like them,
so the children would turn out amazing. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the verse
says, הבו לכם אנשים חכמים ונבונים, Havu lachem anashim chachamim u'nevonim, give
over to yourself people that are wise and understanding, וכתיב ואקח את
ראשי שבטיכם ולא כתיב נבונים, u'chtiv va'ekach et rashei shivteichem v'lo chtiv
nevonim, that they could not have, they didn't have understanding men. The
idea of having תבונה, tevunah, even in Moshe's generation, they could not
find people that had תבונה, tevunah, understanding. וכתיב, U'chtiv, but then it
says, יששכר חמור גרם, Yissachar chamor garem, יששכר Yissachar is like a
bony donkey, וכתיב ומבני יששכר יודעי בינה לעתים, u'chtiv u'mibnei Yissachar yodei
bina l'ittim, that they knew, they had בינה, binah, they had
understanding right, נבונים, nevonim, about the times. So יששכר Yissachar were able
to have children that were נבונים nevonim that you could not find
like them at the time of משה. Moshe. And יששכר Yissachar was
when לאה Leah was תובעת יעקב. tova'at Yaakov. So exactly, so you
see that it's right for a wife to be תובעת tova'at her
husband. The גמרא Gemara says no, ההיא דמרצה ארצויי. hahi d'martza artzuyei.
That's when she's sort of seduces him. You can sort of hint
and seduce, but you can't actually demand.
Right, so now the question comes up, this is also important in
terms of how הלכה Halacha deals with this. Does this really mean
that a wife can't say to her husband, I'd like to have
sex tonight? Is that she can only drop hints? I mean, what's
the line between מרצה ארצויי martza artzuyei and תובעת בפה? tova'at b'peh?
So there's some פוסקים poskim that actually say, like Michael just said,
in the end the גמרא Gemara says
what לאה Leah did was okay. That was on the side of
the column of
מרצה ארצויי. martza artzuyei. When a woman can't be תובעת, tova'at, it
can't be more demanding than לאה. Leah. So what did לאה Leah
say? Basically לאה Leah said, אלי תבוא, Elai tavo, right? How more
explicit can you be? So this is I think the תשובה teshuva
of יהודה יעלה, Yehuda Yaleh, he says, well what the wife can't
say to the husband is, "You must have sex with me tonight,"
like she can't say you have no choice in the matter, buddy,
this is what's happening. Anything less than that would be like לאה
Leah did, so that would be okay. Anyway,
but apparently, so this touches on the idea of the גמרא Gemara
about the wife
as the husband more as the person in control. But it's interesting,
even though that classically was the understanding in patriarchal society or whatever,
the man is the one that initiates and is in control and
so on, in the end, based on the example of לאה Leah
and this line, it becomes a very, and the fact that the
גמרא Gemara even says a very sort of
counter from that ethos, not only does it say it's okay, it
even says the children turn out great, better than they had in
the time of משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. So it's again very interesting,
that recalibration and that rebalancing that happens here. And bottom line is
that after all of this, the real problem is sex that's not
about relating and connecting to the other person. הדרן עלך ואלו מותרין.
Hadran alach ve'elu mutarin. So that was a fascinating end to that
פרק, perek, like the most sort of centralized discussion in the גמרא
Gemara about marital sex.
Yeah, it was also pretty interesting
that although עונה, onah, from what we were learning before in other
מסכתות, masechtot, is really about satisfying the woman. But you would think
that she'd have a say in the matter, you know what I
mean? So it's
a very interesting הוה אמינא hava amina to think that she wouldn't
even be able to say...
No, no, no, that's different. It's different about when she wants to
and, well that's again letting the husband know and making sure that
she's satisfied and is getting pleasure and so on, as opposed to
sort of demanding. And that's exactly the line that's being drawn. Yeah.
And in the earlier section was debate on what's appropriate and not
appropriate, and then discussing what's seen by
versus parts of
your wife, so... Right. So is that also allowed then? And in
other words, how does this all relate to the idea of being
comfortable with your bodies?
What do you mean? That husband and wife looking at parts of
each other's bodies and so on? Yeah, well part of those things
that the גמרא Gemara spoke about that was rejected was looking at
certain places, kissing certain places, and all of that is rejected. Yeah.
Now, again as I said the other day, there are, in a
religious tradition it's understandable that... that that sex can be seen by
some as very problematic like you know because it's so sensual and
powerful and all those types of things and therefore so even though
the position of יוחנן בן זבדא Yochanan ben Zavda seems very resoundingly
rejected here in the גמרא, Gemara, you know for some ראשונים Rishonim
it still they're not ready to fully let go of it. And
therefore it still you know comes up in halakhic discussions. Like the
ראב"ד Raavad says well maybe the גמרא Gemara because the story's about
the woman that came to the רבי Rebbi and רב Rav and
said הפכתה, Hafachta, you know I made a table and he turned
it upside down, says well therefore maybe the גמרא Gemara is only
allowing הפיכת השולחן. Hafichas Hashulchan. Maybe it's not actually allowing you know
it's allowing certain things in terms of the act of intercourse but
maybe it's not allowing נסתכל באותו מקום Nistaklo b'oto makom or נשק
באותו מקום Nishake b'oto makom and so on. You know which is
like so not the פשט Pshat of the גמרא Gemara but again
it's because you you know whatever from a religious position you can
understand how it's hard you know there's two ways you can think
about it like sex is a very positive powerful thing if done
in the right context and completely unproblematic, it's only problematic when it's
like you know done in a wrong way like eating. Eating is
a positive thing if you're doing it right, it's just a problem
when you're doing it wrong, just because there's certain things you're not
allowed to eat doesn't mean that you have to have hang-ups about
eating, right? But then there's the other approach which is no that
sex is fundamentally at odds with like a religious life and we
have to find ways to control it and rein it in or
there's or like there's just a lot of problems there you know.
So many medieval ראשונים Rishonim were some of them were under Christian
influence or
the advent of Islam the way in which it developed.
Right so that's
definitely pre-Christianity
pre-Islamic in a way.
Right. Right so that's also true the question about what to what
did Christianity have an influence? The interesting thing is that רמב"ם Rambam
who is under Islamic influence but he was also under Greek influence
was one of the strongest voices that did see sort of sex
even marital sex as problematic but that had more to do with
his sort of Greek philosophy than it had to do with Islam.
But yes so there's a book if you're interested about this there's
an excellent book called Eros and the Jews by David Biale that
traces from the time of the גמרא Gemara to the modern times
and through Kabbalists and the ספרדים Sephardim and the אשכנזים Ashkenazim and
whatever you know
different attitudes towards sex you know within within Judaism. Okay so let's
now continue. ארבעה נדרים התירו חכמים. Arbaah nedarim hitiru chachamim. So now
a hard to switch gears back here again but we are getting
finally into a different area of נדר Neder which is you know
really central. We've been talking about what did you say? How do
we interpret the words that you say? Did you say the magic
formula? And to what degree can you know you interpret what you
said in a certain way, פירושן להקל. Perushon l'hakel. And the interesting
question is can you give them a bizarre interpretation and it seems
like well basically you can maybe if you're an עם הארץ Am
ha'aretz there's a question if we believe you or not but basically
you know you're believed to interpret and you have to have said
certain types of words. The thing that we sort of did not
get to yet was the idea of פיו ולבו שוים. Piv v'libo
shavin. Like let's say somebody said unambiguous words but he wasn't really
intending to accept upon himself a נדר, Neder, right? It's like you
know that line in what was it Alice in Wonderland where there
was some line about Alice and who was it? Anyway about like
you know say what you mean and or something about the difference
between say what you mean and mean what you say. Anyway
so you English people will anyway find anyway so get the reference
anyway so so the point is you have to both say the
right words and you have to mean what you have said and
that's the issue of פיו ולבו שוים. Piv v'libo shavin. That hasn't
really been fully addressed yet but that's in a way going to
be addressed now. When you actually said the language of נדר Neder
and somehow your frame of mind was such that even though the
words you said were the magic words nevertheless it's not binding because
of what was in what was your frame of mind. Not like
you meant different words you didn't like when you said חרם Cherem
you meant a fish net, no you meant נדר Neder but somehow
your frame of mind was such that nevertheless it's not what you
wanted to do. Okay so let's take a look.
You said what you mean but you didn't mean what you say.
Okay okay. ארבעה נדרים Arbaah nedarim is it Lewis Carroll?
What? he says what he means and means what he says right
Alice in Wonderland 100%.
Oh there you go that's Horton right. ארבעה נדרים התירו חכמים. Arbaah
nedarim hitiru chachamim. So the sages allowed for four types or or
permitted four types of vows that they weren't binding which presumably means
you don't even need to be released from them.
נדרי זירוזין, Nidrei zeruzin, vows of sort of of what's the word
not incitement but of like of stirring of spurring yourself on okay
there's gotta be a better word for that.
Motivational? Alright that's a little too abstract but okay spurring vows. I'll
do with spurring. נדרי הבאי, Nidrei havai, vows of nothingness that you
weren't serious about them. ונדרי שגגות, V'nidrei shegagos, ones that you made
in error. ונדרי אונסין, V'nidrei onsin, and ones that you were forced
and compelled to make. Okay so each one of these is has
to do with you said the words and those words were vow
words and you knew they were vow words and nevertheless because your
frame of mind was not in sync with that. So let's take
a Let's take a look. נדרי זירוזין, Nidrei Zeruzin, כיצד, keitzad, spurring
vows, as it's for example, היה מוכר חפץ, hayah mocher chefetz, you
are selling an object to somebody, ואומר, ve'omeir, קונם שאני פוחת לך
מן הסלע, Konam she-ani pocheis lach min ha-sela, you know, this object
should be forbidden to you if I sell it to you for
anything less than a סלע, sela, four זוז, zuz, okay, 40 bucks.
Haggling, right. והוא אומר, ve-hu omeir, קונם שאני מוסיף לך על הסלע,
Konam she-ani mosif lach al ha-sela, this object should be forbidden to
me if I go any higher than 20 bucks, a שקל, shekel,
excuse me, a שקל shekel which is two זוז, zuz, okay. שניהם
רוצים בשלשה דינרים, Shneihem rotzim b'shloshah dinarim, they're both trying to get
to 30 bucks, okay, to three. All right, so therefore they don't
really mean to forbid it, it's just part of the haggling, it's
to show, you know, and therefore nobody is really serious about it.
Yes, they knew what the words meant, but they were not serious
about it. Okay, so that's this problem of טיבי לביה
בשבועה,
tivi
libeih
b'shvuah, it could be like a problem.
Well, it might be that these are true בשבועה bishvuah as well,
but anyway. ארבעה נדרים התירו חכמים. Arba'ah nedarim hitiru chachamim. אמר ליה
רב אבא, Amar lei Rav Abba, top of כ''ה ע''א, chaf heh
amud aleph, אמר ליה רב אבא בר ממל לרבי אמי. Amar lei
Rav Abba bar Mamal l'Rabbi Ami. אמרת לן משמיה דרבי יהודה נשיאה,
Amart lan mishmeih d'Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah, you told us in the name
of רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah, not to be confused with
רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, רבי יהודה נשיאה Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah
was his grandson. מאן תנא ארבעה נדרים? Man tana arba'ah nedarim? Who
is the author of
ארבעה נדרים? arba'ah nedarim? רבי יהודי, Rabbi Yehudi, it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, a third רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that's רבי יהודה בר אלעאי.
Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai. דאמר משום רבי טרפון, D'amar mishum Rabbi Tarfon,
לעולם אינו נזיר לפי שלא ניתנה נזירות אלא להפלאה. L'olam eino nazir
lefi shelo nitnah nezirut ela l'hafla'ah. Remember that? So I say, I
am a נזיר nazir if that guy walking down the street is
Joe. And David here says, I'm a... what are you talking about?
You're crazy. That's not Joe. I'll be a נזיר nazir if whatever...
that is Joe. And I'll say I'll be a נזיר nazir if
it's not Joe. So one of us should be a נזיר. nazir.
And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the name of רבי טרפון Rabbi
Tarfon says neither of us is a נזיר nazir because it's not...
it was not clear at the time it was taken whether or
not it was, you know, that it would be binding. Okay, it
has to be precise. הפלאה Hafla'ah means precise. Now, how is that
relevant to this סוגיא sugya of the זירוזין? zeruzin? Well, he sort
of sees this זירוזין zeruzin case as like... as like a... there's
an 'if', right? If, you know, I go up, or if I
go down, let it be אסור, assur, so any conditional נדר, neder,
like any conditional נזירות, nezirut, shouldn't be binding because it has to
be absolute, unquestionable, precise at the time that it is uttered. That's
why. So it's not because, here's the important point, it's not because
it's not serious. I could have been totally serious. And even if
I was totally serious, it's not binding because it was based on
a stipulation. That's not what the משנה mishnah seems to be saying,
which is what the גמרא gemara pushes back. So let's take a
look. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, אפילו תימא רבנן. Afilu
teima rabanan. No, it can even be the rabbis that argue and
say in that case of the נזירות, nezirut, whichever one's condition is
met is a נזיר. nazir. But מי קתני שניהם רצו? Mi katani
shneihem ratzu? We're not saying that they both wanted something else, meaning
and therefore they, you know... they were serious, but nevertheless since it
was based on some type of a condition and the condition, you
know, therefore it's not חל. chal. שניהם רוצים קתני. Shneihem rotzim katani.
We say they want, from the very outset they weren't serious. Okay?
So it's not because they were serious but because, you know, it
was stipulated, therefore it's not binding. You know, we're saying that because,
no, that they from the very outset never wanted it to be
binding and were not serious. And that's the point here. Okay. אמר
ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi, רבינא Ravina said
to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, אמר לו טפי מסלע, Amar lo tfei
misela, ואמר בציר משקל. v'amar batzir mishekel. Let's say the guy said,
I won't go lower than, you know, 40 dollars and one cent.
And the other one says I won't go any higher than 1.99.
Let's do... let's not do tens, let's do ones. I won't go
any lower than 4 dollars and one cent. And the other say
I won't go any higher than 1.99, okay, a שקל. shekel. So
because now they're not saying just four and two, they're being more
precise, maybe they're serious. If you only wanted to get to three,
you would not be so precise, you would say four and two.
If you're saying 4 dollars and one cent and 1.99...
you do things at like 3.99, 9.99.
That's what you're selling, so that's not what you're how you're haggling.
Okay, anyway, but maybe you're right, you could say the same thing.
When you go from 1.99 to 2 it sounds like more of
a concession. Anyway, so what do we say? רבא אמר, Rava amar,
מי קתני... mi katani... okay.
טפי מסלע ואמר בציר משקל. Tfei misela v'amar batzir mishekel. נדרא הוי
או זירוזין הוי? Nidra havei o zeruzin havei? Is it a real
נדר neder or is it just a spurring type of a thing?
אמר ליה תנינא, Amar lei tanina, we taught: היה מסרב בחבירו שיאכל
אצלו, Hayah mesareiv bachaveiro she-yochal etzlo, you were trying to press your
friend to eat by
you. ואמר לו, v'amar lo, קונם ביתך שאני נכנס, Konam beitecha she-ani
nichnas, your house should be forbidden to me that I won't go
into it. טפת צונן שאני טועם, Tipat tzonen she-ani toeim, or even
a drop of like cold water that I won't drink it, okay.
מותר ליכנס לביתו ולשתות הימנו צונן, Mutar licanes l'veito v'lishtot heimenu tzonen,
you're actually, it's not binding. It sounds like a pretty big נדר.
neder. שלא נתכוון זה אלא לשום אכילה ושתיה, Shelo nitkavein zeh ela
l'shum achilah u-shtiyah, that this person
only was intended for like לשום אכילה ושתיה, l'shum achilah u-shtiyah, which
means what? So if you take a look at the ר''ן, Ran,
he says... אמר אף על גב דנחית לדיוקא, Amar af al gav
d'nachis l'diyuka, the two lines on the
bottom, even though he's being very precise and saying like I won't
even step into your house, I won't even take a drop of
water. ונתרחק הרבה ממה שהיה רוצה חבירו, V'nitrachak harbeh mima she-hayah rotzeh
chaveiro, and was very distanced from what his friend wanted. really mean
it, you really just meant like you know you just wanted to
like you know you know it was just a it was just
again like a type of an exaggeration. Okay, let me just see
something. You don't want to have a full meal there but to
have like a glass of water is you know. Well one minute
hold on hold on. Right, because exactly, because what you're doing is
I just remind myself. So what you're doing is is that is
that you really did not literally mean you wouldn't go into the
house. You say come on come on come on come on come
on have a nice שבת Shabbos dinner with me and I'm like
fed up and I won't even go to your house. So I
really don't not want to go into your house, I just don't
want to have the שבת Shabbos dinner, okay? So therefore that's an
interesting case. It's not exactly by the way the case in our
משנה. Mishna. In our משנה Mishna you didn't mean the נדר Neder
at all, right? And that's actually going to be a question that
the גמרא Gemara is going to get to. Like let's say the
guy says a נדר Neder that I'm not going to go less
than four, okay?
Right and I really am prepared to go to three, okay?
If I settled at two, would the נדר Neder be binding? If
I really never would have wanted to have gone less than four,
so even though I said four I meant three. So is it
binding when I go lower than three? Or is it not binding
at all because it wasn't really I really didn't mean it? So
that type of a case you have here. The guy says come
eat at my house and I say נדר Neder I'm not even
your whole house is forbidden to me. So I didn't mean the
whole house is forbidden I didn't really want to make the whole
house forbidden but maybe I still made the eating with like the
dinner with you forbidden because that I did want. So it was
just the exaggerated part falls off but the core part remains or
do we say since the whole thing is an exaggeration nothing remains?
Okay, so that's the ברייתא Braita the way it's understood is more
that the exaggerated part falls off. It says let's read it again,
מותר ליכנס לביתו ולשתות צונן. mutar likaneis l'veito v'lishtot tzonen. You're it's
it doesn't say you're מותר mutar to have the meal. Somehow we're
assuming like the core part of the נדר Neder remains but you
what drops off is the exaggerated part of the נדר. Neder. You
can go into the house and you can drink. שלא נתכוון אלא
לשום אכילה ושתיה. she'lo nitkavein ela l'shum achila u'shtiya. What you really
wanted to do is forbid having a real meal in the guy's
house, that part remains, the exaggerated part falls off. So number one
that's a big חידוש, chiddush, right? That we can say it's not
an all or nothing type of a thing, we can eliminate the
exaggerated extension and go to the core. Okay so again in the
case by the haggling it could be lower than three would be
forbidden. Who knows, we'll see. Anyway how's this relevant to our case?
דאמאי וטיפה צונן קאמר? d'amai v'atipa tzonen ka'mar? He obviously is speaking
even in tiny amounts. So if he's speaking about tiny amounts we
should say that maybe he means it literally. He didn't say you
know I won't like like all drinking and eating and going into
the house, a drop is like precise. It seems to be precise.
Of course it's funny, it's really exaggerated language, but anyway, alright, that's
the way the גמרא Gemara is understanding it. So even though he
went to be so precise about a drop, okay it's a measurement,
that shows that even when you're being a measurement you can still
mean it not be literal about it. אלא משתעי אינשי הכי, ela
mishtayei she'hachi, that's the way people talk. הכי נמי משתעי אינשי הכי,
hachi nami mishtayei she'hachi, here too people talk that way. It's still
a little funny. If you say I won't drink a drop that's
clearly language of exaggeration. If you say I won't go higher than
a dollar and 74 cents, okay that's not exactly language of exaggeration,
that's language of precision. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה, amlei,
he said back to him, כפוף עמוד ב, kfof amud bet, מי
דמי? mi dami? How can you compare it? גבי צונן gabei tzonen
צדיקים אומרים מעט ועושים הרבה. tzaddikim omrim me'at v'osim harbeh. By the
cold water righteous people say a little and do a lot. הכא
ספיקא הוא, hakha sfeka hu, here it's a doubt. דילמא פחות מסלע
ויותר משקל קאמר, dilma pachat mi'selah v'yoteir mi'shekel ka'mar, maybe
they really mean they don't want to you know it's just like
talking about going lower than a סלע selah or more than a
שקל shekel וזירוזין הוי, v'ziruzan havei, and it's your standard language of
spurring. או דילמא דוקא קאמר, o dilma davka ka'mar, or maybe they
really mean a dollar 78, I won't go lower than four dollars
and 23 cents, ונדר הוי, v'nedar havei, it's a real נדר. Neder.
תיקו, teiku, so תיקו, teiku, meaning we don't know, that's a question.
Now what is the response of צדיקים אומרים מעט ועושים הרבה? tzaddikim
omrim me'at v'osim harbeh? It's not so clear, but basically what it
means is that maybe here the reason I say I won't even
take a drop of liquid in your house is because if I
agreed to a drop of liquid I know you'll say okay okay
okay fine just come over for a drop of liquid and then
before I'm going to come over for a drop of liquid and
I'm going to want if I'm such a צדיק tzaddik I don't
want you to be over on your נדר Neder whatever. But basically
you don't want to get yourself into that situation so you really
did mean you didn't want to do even the smallest amount. But
of course the funny thing is wait a minute, but if that's
what you really did mean then why isn't it binding? Right? So
like what's the logic? You know? So it sounds like it's really
it's not clear. It sounds like it's like the reverse. The same
way צדיקים tzaddikim say a lot promise a little and do a
lot if you want to stop yourself from doing a lot you
will stop yourself you'll use a language of doing a little. Of
even doing a little. Which basically means that like not that you
the same way when you promise
So when you promise something, even if אברהם Avraham said I'll give
you a tiny drop of water, I'll just give you a one
liter bottle of water, right, and he would say one liter bottle
of water but he'd give you a big feast. So that's the
way it works when you're talking about those things. You'll say less
than you mean or you'll say more than you mean and you
mean
it in this exaggerated type of a way, okay, or in this
under-exaggerated type of a way. But that's a way of talking, you
downplay what you're going to do or you in this case are
extreme about what you're going to do, but you don't literally mean
it. But here when you use a precise, not a promise of
what you'll do or won't do for somebody, but a precise number
in a, you know, financial haggling, maybe you really mean to be
precise. Okay, so we don't know. But again, what's interesting beyond the
question of precision is that do we say just the exaggerated part
drops off or do we say the whole נדר neder drops off?
So let's take a look. Okay, אמר רב
אסי,
Amar Rav
Assi, said רב אסי. Rav Assi. ארבעה נדרים הללו—I'm Arbaah nedarim hallalu
sorry, did I skip a line? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Assi, ארבעה נדרים הללו צריכין שאלה לחכם.
Arbaah nedarim hallalu tzerichin sheelah lehacham.
When you make any of these four נדרים, nedarim, so somebody in
this haggling case—remember we had this before—if it looks too close to
a נדר, neder, even if it's not a נדר, neder, in order
so that you don't treat it leniently, we're going to make you
go through a process of freeing yourself from it. Like the guy
says, oh I didn't really mean a נדר, neder, I really meant
like a fishnet. Okay, so then we're going to make you go
through the process of getting yourself released from the vow. So here
he's saying these four although the language is the חכמים chachamim permitted
it, which sounds like it's not a problem at all, we're actually
going to make somebody go through a process of getting released from
the vow. So Michael and I were haggling—right, every single day, it's
like we'll set up shop at the end of every market day
for everybody who made all their vows, right? Maybe we can charge
a dollar for a visit, we'll make a lot of money off
of it. Okay, so anyway, okay, so he says, okay, צריכין שאלה
לחכם. tzerichin sheelah lehacham. כי אמריתה קמי דשמואל Ki amriteh kamei diShmuel
when I said it to שמואל, Shmuel, אמר amar
he said, תנא תני ארבעה נדרים התירו חכמים, Tanna tani arbaah nedarim
hittiru chachamim,
our תנא tanna teaches that the חכמים chachamim permitted them, which means
it's completely non-problematic, like it's automatically permissible. Meaning, maybe we're not saying
לכתחילה lchatchilah you should do it, but it certainly sounds like there's
no—if it's done, it's not a problem, okay? ואת אמרת צריכין שאלה
לחכם ve-at amrat tzerichin sheelah lehacham and you say you need to
go through a process of being released from them? No, because automatically
they aren't binding. And it's not like, again, those cases we had
yesterday, which seemed more to be binding and needed a process of
being released even if technically they were okay. This is clear that
it's not a problem and therefore you don't need this process of
being released from it. רב יוסף מתני להא, Rav Yosef matni lehachai,
so therefore here's how רב יוסף Rav Yosef teaches it, מתני להא
שמעתא בהאי לישנא matni lehachai shamata behai lishana here's how he teaches
it because that one ends with a challenge like, you know, how
could you say you need to be released from it? אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Assi, אין חכם
רשאי להתיר, ein chacham rashai lehattir,
here's a different version of it which is not challenged, a sage
is not allowed to permit a נדר neder אלא כעין ארבעה נדרים
הללו ella ke-ein arbaah nedarim hallalu unless it gets to similar to
these four categories. And now what we're going to do is shift
gear. Okay, we start from if you say something you don't mean
in a נדרי זירוזין nidrei zerozin just to spur the other person
on, it's not a נדר. neder. Now remember the reason is because
you weren't really intending for—you never really meant for it to be
binding. Okay, keep that in mind. But now we're going to say
that is a model for us for the normal הלכה halacha of
התרת נדרים. hattarat nedarim. Michael comes to me and says a week
ago I made a נדר neder that, you know, whatever, I'm not
going to eat any apples. Gave me a big stomach ache the
other day, I made a נדר neder I'm not going to eat
apples. But you know what, I realized it was because of something
I had before, I really don't want to make that נדר, neder,
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is coming up, so anyway I want to
eat apples on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, I need you to be
מתיר matir my נדר. neder. Okay, so now the question is how
much evidence do I need that
he—to construct it that it's clear that he never meant it? And
we're going to use the paradigm of something that doesn't require התרת
נדרים, hattarat nedarim, right? The guy's haggling in the marketplace, that doesn't
require התרת נדרים, hattarat nedarim, that's obvious to everyone that they never
meant their נדר. neder. This case by Michael certainly looked like that—that's
clear, you know, that that was a נדר. neder. So if I'm
going to מתיר matir it, if I'm going to מתיר matir it,
maybe I should—here's the statement—I can only מתיר matir his נדר neder
if I can get it somewhat to approximate this idea of haggling
in the marketplace, meaning if I can make it somewhat evident that
under certain circumstances he never meant it.
Or נדרי שגגות nidrei shegagot or נדרי אונסין. nidrei anusin.
Right, exactly, but let's focus on this one because this is the
one we know. Now you understand that, right, that this is the
core, the core of התרת נדרים, hattarat nedarim, what is the core
of the process of התרת נדרים? hattarat nedarim? It basically is the
same point of this משנה. mishna. The core of התרת נדרים hattarat
nedarim is in hindsight I never wanted—חרטה charata is in hindsight I
never wanted to have made it. So when I—at the time I
made it, did I really want it? Yes. But looking back, knowing
what I—you know, I can say I wish I had it made.
So it's a little funny but what we're sort of doing is
we're projecting your frame of mind. now and saying like had I
known then what I know now, or now I wish in hindsight,
or we'll see actually because if you really then did want it,
well we'll get, I'm confusing things. We'll get to חרטה Charata in
a minute. Hold off on חרטה, Charata, I'm sorry, I confused things.
Let's deal with פתח Petach because that's the focus. What's the core
of פתח? Petach? The core of פתח Petach is had I been
thinking through the fact that ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah was around the
bend, right, I wouldn't have made my vow against apples. That's like
a חרטה Charata case, okay, which basically means that had I- that's
the פתח Petach case. Thank you, sorry, that's the פתח Petach case.
Which basically means that, although I intended it, I wasn't thinking that
clearly, and had I really thought that clearly, I really wouldn't have
wanted to do it. So it's somewhat similar to the case where
I very clearly know I don't want to do it, we're just
haggling, I obviously don't mean what I'm saying. Here, I said I
meant what I'm saying, but it wasn't fully in sync with my
desire because I haven't fully thought things through. Okay, so that's somewhat
similar. It's not like I consciously not what I want to do,
consciously I want to do it, but it's not fully in sync
with what my desire is because I haven't thought through all the
issues. Okay, so that's what he is saying. Let's read that again,
and this is very much where we're going to focus on the
process of התרת נדרים. Hataras Nedarim. Okay. So, אין חכם משתת כעין
ארבעה נדרים הללו. Ein chacham mashtet ke'ein arba nedarim hallalu. קסבר, Kasavar,
he's of the opinion אין פותחין בחרטה. ein potchin becharata. You don't
start by saying like, oh, do you regret ever having made it?
Because even if I say yes, I regret ever having made it,
that's not like saying like at the time had I thought about
the following thing I wouldn't have made it, which is the פתח.
Petach. If you can say had I thought about the following thing
I wouldn't have made it, that's similar to the ארבעה נדרים הללו.
arba nedarim hallalu. It's similar to the idea like you never really
meant it. There's a case where you consciously never really meant it,
where you were just haggling, and there's a case where you never
meant it because had you thought it through, you would not have
done it. Okay, so that we can do. We can do a
פתח Petach because that's similar to the ארבעה נדרים. arba nedarim. It's
getting us to a place where we can say at the time
you didn't mean it. And that's not the same as חרטה, Charata,
which is at the time actually I did mean it. Okay, I
was very angry, I was really angry at you at the time,
at that time had you said, you know, you're going to regret
this later on, did you think about this, etc. Nevertheless, at the
time I would have said I don't care, I'm so angry at
this person, whatever. So that there's no question that at the time
I meant it. It's just now that I've calmed down, okay, now
I wish I hadn't done it. Okay, but that's a little different
than saying that we can say that at the time you didn't
fully mean it. All right, so that's what he says. So אין
פותחין בחרטה ein potchin becharata means we would allow to start with
a פתח Petach but not a חרטה. Charata. Exactly, you start with
a פתח. Petach. Now we're not saying a חרטה Charata won't work
if you can't find a פתח, Petach, okay, but you certainly don't
start with the חרטה Charata process. So we're using again, sorry if
I keep on repeating this, but trying to get this clear, the
idea of the ארבעה נדרים הללו arba nedarim hallalu is when you
are not basically really intending for the vow to be binding. Okay,
I was only haggling, I was only whatever, I wouldn't really want
the vow to be binding. That lies at the core of התרת
נדרים על ידי פתח. Hataras Nedarim al yedei petach. התרת נדרים על
ידי פתח Hataras Nedarim al yedei petach is I did think I
wanted it to be binding, but I'm going to help you realize
that you really didn't want it to be binding at that time,
that had you thought through the issues, you wouldn't have wanted it.
And that's very, and that's at the core of this פיו ולבו
שוין, piv velibo shavin, did I really want it to be binding,
okay? So that's the way you have to go is through the
פתח. Petach. אין פותחין בחרטה. Ein potchin becharata. ההוא. Hahu. Now, again,
I want to repeat for those also to remind us about a
חרטה Charata point, which is a point that the ר"ן Ran makes
which is really important, that there are two types of חרטה. Charata.
There's the חרטה Charata which is, I really am happy that I
made it for the last year, I just I just now נתחרטתי
nischaratti that I'm still bound by it. Like I took a vow
against all carbs, right, because I wanted to do my Atkins thing,
and that was good, that got me to lose 20 pounds off
over the last year, but now I need to go back to
a normal diet. So I don't regret having done it for the
last year, I just regret that I'm still bound by it. That
is not חרטה. Charata. That's every נדר. neder. Every נדר, neder, the
reason you're showing up at my door is because now you don't
want to be bound by it. חרטה Charata is like, you know,
I never should have made it in the first place. There's no
way I can say that at the time, knowing what my frame
of mind was at the time, there is no way I could
say that I wouldn't have made it at the time. But I
can say that in hindsight I wish I had never made it
in the first place. Okay, that's like less obvious why that should
get you out of it, but that's what חרטה Charata is. Are
you saying the difference is between חרטה מעיקרא Charata me'ikara and חרטה
דהשתא? Charata dehashtah? Exactly. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרב הונא. Hahu de'ata lekamei deRav Huna. A
person came to רב הונא. Rav Huna. אמר ליה, Amar lei, רב
הונא Rav Huna said to him, ליבך עלך? Libecha alecha? Is your
heart on you? אמר ליה, לא. Amar lei lo, No. ושריא. Vesharyei.
And he permitted him. So what does that mean? So basically what
the ר"ן Ran tries to do is he basically tries to interpret
this as this case of this חרטה Charata of מעיקרא, me'ikara, which
means, wait. Right. He basically says were you like in the same
frame of mind, you know, all along that well let's take a
look at the ר"ן. Ran. ליבך לך, Libcha lecha, it's about ten
lines before the medium line. כלומר היה ליבך מיושב עליך בשעה שנדרת,
Klomar haya libcha meyushav alecha beshaa shenadarta, were you in a calm
state of mind when you made the נדר? neder? וגם עכשיו אינך
תוהה בנדרך עד היום, Vigam achshav aincha toheh binidrecha ad hayom, and
now also you don't regret having made it until today, אלא שמהיום
ולהלן אתה רוצה לחזור בך, Ela shemehayom ulehalan ata rotzeh lachzor bach,
or now is when you don't want to do it. והוי כי
האי גוונא, Vihavei kehai gavna, and if that's true, then it's you
were totally, you know, it's you know you're totally sort of in
a calm state of mind and only now you want it not
to be binding, then לא חרטה דעיקרא היא, Lo charatah de'ikara hi,
that's not a חרטה, charata, דחרטה דעיקרא בעינן, Decharatah de'ikara bainan, because
we need it that you regret ever having made it.
או לא היה ליבך מיושב עליך,
O
lo
haya libcha meyushav alecha, or maybe at the time you were not
of your right frame
of mind, you know, you were not sort of you know in
how you're thinking now, שמתוך הכעס נדרתי, Shemitoch haka'as nadarti, you were
angry, ועכשיו אתה תוהה על הראשונות, Viachshav ata toheh al harishonot, and
now you're upset about. So somehow ליבך עליך Libcha alecha is a
way of saying like like were you, you know, you know, do
you, you know, are you of the same frame of mind than
you were before? Do you regret having, you know, having ever made
the נדר neder in the first place? So it's a little hard
to exactly map that onto the words, but basically it's a way
of saying are you just changing your mind now or do you
regret ever having made it in the first place? And somehow the
answer of no means no, I am not just changing my mind
now, I actually, you know, regret having made it in the first
place and therefore he was מתיר, matir, which basically means he was
מתיר matir by חרטה, charata, not being מתיר matir by פתח. petach.
He didn't say to them had you thought about this or whatever,
he just said what's your what was your frame of mind. And
if now you actually regret, you know, having made it, then it's
not binding. Yes. Do you see parallels with the process of תשובה
teshuva thing? That's a good point. Oh because that is the word
חרטה, charata, right, and then you're not to do it again. Yeah,
it's a good right exactly, you're correct about that. Okay. Okay, קסבר
kasavar where were we. Okay,
so that's a counter-proof that you are פותח בחרטה. potein bicharata. ההוא
דאתא לקמיה דרבה בר בר חנה, Hahu de'ata likamei deRabba bar bar
Chana, somebody came to Rabba bar bar Chana. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
אלו היו עשרה בני אדם שיפייסוך באותה שעה, Ilu hayu asara binei
adam sheyefaysucha be'ota shaa, if there would be ten people at that
time that would have like calmed you down, you were angry at
your friend and right you were angry at somebody, if there had
been ten people that had tried to persuade you and calm you
down and so on, מי נדרת, Mi nadarta, would you have still
made a vow? אמר ליה Amar lei, לא, Lo. no then I
wouldn't have made the vow. והתירו, Vehitiro, and he permitted it. So
is that a פתח petach or is that a חרטה? charata? So
the ר"ן Ran says there are two גרסאות girsas of this גמרא.
Gemara. One גרסא girsa is you see that אין פותקין בחרטה ein
potkin bicharata and the other גרסא girsa is you see that פותקין
בחרטה. potkin bicharata. Because basically what he says is this is a
little bit more than a חרטה charata but a little less than
a פתח. petach. A חרטה charata is you don't have to tell
me had I known that there were ten friends. Right, a חרטה
charata was just do you regret having made it and I would
say yes. So to tell me had ten friends intervened would you
have made it, that's like a more considering the circumstances that I
wouldn't have even made it at that time, that's a little less
than a standard חרטה, charata, that's a little like, you know, better
than a standard חרטה charata because there's a way in which I
wouldn't have made it at the same time, but it's a little
worse than a standard פתח. petach. Right, a standard פתח petach is
just like I didn't think the issue through with all its implications.
Here what I'm saying is if there had been somebody to come
along and persuade me to change my mind I would have changed
my mind. Okay, that's different than saying I myself didn't stop to
think through all the implications. So this is like an a middle
ground between פתח petach and חרטה. charata. Okay, תניא רבי יהודה אומר,
Tanya Rabbi Yehuda omer, אומרים לו לאדם, Omrim lo leadam, you say
to a person, לב זה עליך, Lev zeh alecha, is is is
your same sort of heart upon you? אם אמר לא, Im amar
lo, if he says no, מתירין אותו, Matirin oto, you permit him.
Again the ר"ן Ran says what that basically means is you say
to him, you know, basically are you like okay with what you
had done in the past and now you've just changed your mind?
He says no, I'm not okay with what I did in the
past, I really wish I hadn't done it, then we permit it.
So again that is an example of חרטה. charata. חרטה charata is
just I wish I hadn't done it.
Okay.
תניא Tanya
what.
Exactly. Well no but this is right this is the position פותקין
בחרטה potkin bicharata as opposed to the position of אין פותקין בחרטה.
ein potkin bicharata. So this is the big ongoing debate about פותקין
או אין פותקין בחרטה. potkin o ein potkin bicharata. I will tell
you I once was on a בית דין beit din where it
was a התרת נדרים, hatarat nedarim, I mean a you know not
a בית דין, beit din, I mean somebody asked me because you
can do it as a יחיד yachid also, but anyway, but then
I can be in a
בית דין. beit din. Anyway, so
where it's not always easy to get either. Somebody really had taken
a נדר neder and they really were to get themselves to be
more careful about something and were really happy, you know, were really
like if they were being honest were like glad that they had
done that for the period of time but now it didn't make
any more sense for them in terms of their lives. So you
could, you didn't have like a, you know, you didn't have a
חרטה charata and then to try to figure out a פתח, petach,
like the פתח petach was like had you realized it would have
been so hard would you have done it, it's like well you...
Yeah, that's why I did it. I did it because I knew
it would be hard and I wanted to force myself to do
it anyway. So it was really very hard to figure out what
like a פתח petach was there.
You could had you imagined that you would reach the point where
you wouldn't need that anymore?
Right, right, right.
That phrase differently, but
not imaginable in it for his
whole life.
Right, right.
So that's I think that's where I went. I don't remember exactly
how I got there, but it was something like that. Like, like
yes, you wanted it to help you sort of commit to certain
things even though you found them difficult, but maybe had you really
thought through about whether this is something you wanted to be doing
your whole life or thought that you would get to a point
in your life where you wouldn't need to do that, would you
still have wanted to? You know, so yeah, that's something along those
lines. But you know, it's, you know, or at least you wouldn't
have wanted to have done it that it was a נדר neder
without, you know, that you wouldn't have wanted to do it that
it was a נדר, neder, that's the question. Let's say, so well,
I would have still wanted to take a נדר neder but I
would have maybe wanted to have made it more conditional or maybe
more time-bound and so on. Yeah. So take a step back for
a second,
you make a נדר neder not to eat any apples. Yeah. Ever.
Well, that apples are forbidden on you, yeah.
I קונם konam apples. Right. I'm not
saying, but you might say that. You eat an apple. You have
to bring what do you have to do you have to bring
an offering?
What do you have to? No, you transgress a negative prohibition of
לא יחל דברו. lo yachel devaro. Get lashes? Yeah, if you if
there were warning and you did it במזיד, be-meizid, right.
Okay, so you you eat an apple then you're like oh you
you broke your נדר. neder. Right.
You don't get it annulled.
Right. You eat the next apple, you get another set of lashes.
So so your נדר neder doesn't go away. Exactly. So it's meritorious
to keep going with your נדר neder even after you break it
once.
Not meritorious, it's binding on you, yeah. Yeah. All right, let's keep
on going.
Because we don't start חרטה charata because we take words seriously.
That's a good point, it's a good point. You're right. Meaning it's
not just a social point that makes things too easy and undermines
the seriousness, but because it's actually that is the power of נדר,
neder, of the language. Exactly. Okay. All right. Okay, תניא, tanya, let's
see inside. רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Ishmael b'Rabbi Yose אומר משום
אביו, omer mishum aviv, אומרין לו לאדם, omrin lo l'adam, you say
to a person, אילו היו עשרה בני אדם שפייסוך באותה שעה מי
נדרת, ilu hayu asara benei adam she-yifaysukha be-ota sha'a mi-nadarta, אם אמר
לאו, im amar lav, מתירין אותו. matirin oto. So actually, so again,
if 10 people had persuaded you, which is a little bit more
than חרטה, charata, it's not just you regret it, right, it's actually
could you have been persuaded otherwise? But it's a little less than
פתח petach because it's sort of like had somebody persuaded you to
change your mind as opposed to had you just thought through the
implications. Okay, ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרב אסי. hahu d'ata lekamei d'Rav Assi.
Somebody came to Rav Assi. אמר לו, Amar lo, he said to
him, כדו תהיתא, kiduta shita, are you like astounded at what you
had done originally? Like are you like regretful? אמר ליה, Amar lei,
לא, lo, no, ושריה, ve-sharyei, and he permitted. So it's like some
of these cases are bizarre, you really want them to be saying
yes when they're saying no. Like the Ran says he said it
like bitmi'a, am I not? Of course, am I not astounded? I
get it. Anyway, it's clear what's going on here. It's not exactly
clear the idiomatic expression. Basically the point was was like you are
regretful of ever having done it.
So again that's a case of a How how are you translating
it again?
כדו תהיתא? kiduta shita? Are you like To be תוהה על הראשונה,
toheh al harishona, like regretful. Yeah, you got the key out?
The door, we can't use no key for it. Now we had
to take the whole door apart because the lance is already disarmed.
You put the key in there, the key got trapped.
So I'm really sorry about that. Nobody told me about that.
The supposedly the entrance through the kitchen, that's the only key you
can use, those keys you can't use. So I was never told
about that, I'm very sorry. The key only for for inside.
You know, they changed the
doors, nobody ever told me about that, I'm very sorry.
That they didn't tell me that that side the key got trapped.
Yeah. So now I had to take everything apart, now it's a
problem.
I'm very sorry. Be nice if they would have told me. All
right. Okay. אמר ליה לא ושריה. Amar lei lo v'sharyei. ההוא דאתא,
Hahu d'ata, we'll do one more story, ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבי אליעזר.
hahu d'ata lekamei d'Rabbi Eliezer. אמר ליה, Amar lei, בעית נדור? be-ita
nadur? Would you do you want to and do you want remaining
in the vow? Right. Right, do you want to I'm just looking
at the Ran do you want your נדר neder until now? Are
you only changing your mind now?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, אילו
לא מרגיזין לי, ilu lo margizin li, if they had not got
me so angry at
that
time, לא בעינן כלום, lo be-inan klum, then I
would never have made the vow. אמר ליה, Amar lei, תהא כבעית,
tehei k'va'is, let it be like you wanted. Meaning fine, so the
vow is not binding, you only made the vow because you were
angry, but you really wish you had never made that vow and
never you wish those circumstances had never occurred. ההיא איתתא, Hahi itta,
one more case, a certain woman דאדרתה לברתה d'adarta l'barta that she
that she made her daughter forbidden to get benefit from her, that
her daughter was forbidden to get benefit from the mother. אתא לקמיה
דרבי יוחנן. Ata lekamei d'Rabbi Yochanan. Then she went to Rabbi Yochanan
to get release from the vow. אמר לה, Amar lah, he said
to her, אילו הוית ידעת, ilu avita yadat, had you known דאמרין
מגירתיך, d'amrin megirataikh, that your neighbors would have said, עלה דברתך, ala
d'bartakh, אילו לא חמא בת אימא, ilu lo khama bat imma, had
her mother not seen her, מילין דעזיבה, milin d'aziva, you know, things
that were worth like abandoning her, like abandoning her. really terrible things,
בכדי לא אדרתה, bechdi lo adarta, she never would have vowed for
no reason. The fact that her mother made her forbidden in benefit
must mean that this daughter had done horrific things, meaning they would
have sort of thought all these bad stuff about your daughter, not
just that you had a fit of anger. So מי אדרת, mi
adart, would you have taken the vow? אמרה ליה, amra leh, no,
she said no, ושריה, v'sharya, and therefore permitted her. So therefore the
mother, so that's a case where this actually is a good example
of a פתח, petach, right? Had you stopped to think through what
the implications of this vow would have been, even the social implications
of this vow, would you have taken it? And she said no,
so that's a perfect example, so then you really didn't mean it
at the time. Now, you know, your full sense of, you were
doing this through incomplete information. Exactly. Had you realized what the neighbors
would start to say? Exactly. Exactly. Yeah, that's why it's good to
have neighbors.